[
  {
    "id": 1,
    "question": "Which one of the following dynasties ruled Kerala ?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Chera Dynasty",
      "B": "Maurya Dynasty",
      "C": "Nanda Dynasty",
      "D": "None of the above"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "A",
    "category": "History & Geography",
    "correct_answer_text": "Chera Dynasty"
  },
  {
    "id": 2,
    "question": "The United Kerala Convention of 1947 was held at",
    "options": {
      "A": "Thrissur",
      "B": "Ottapalam",
      "C": "Kochi",
      "D": "Kozhikode"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "A",
    "category": "Movements & Politics",
    "correct_answer_text": "Thrissur"
  },
  {
    "id": 3,
    "question": "What is the area of Kerala state?",
    "options": {
      "A": "32,863 km²",
      "B": "31,863 km²",
      "C": "38,863 km²",
      "D": "None of the above"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "C",
    "category": "History & Geography",
    "correct_answer_text": "38,863 km²"
  },
  {
    "id": 4,
    "question": "Who founded 'Prathyaksha Raksha Sabha'?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Pandit Karuppan",
      "B": "TK Madhavan",
      "C": "Poikayil Kumara Devan",
      "D": "Ayyankali"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "C",
    "category": "Social Reformers & Leaders",
    "correct_answer_text": "Poikayil Kumara Devan"
  },
  {
    "id": 5,
    "question": "What was the name of the first Governor of Kerala?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Bhagwan Sahay",
      "B": "Burgula Ramkrishna Rao",
      "C": "V. V. Giri",
      "D": "None of the above"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "B",
    "category": "Social Reformers & Leaders",
    "correct_answer_text": "Burgula Ramkrishna Rao"
  },
  {
    "id": 6,
    "question": "When was Kerala state formed ?",
    "options": {
      "A": "1 November 1956",
      "B": "1 November 1957",
      "C": "1 November 1958",
      "D": "1 November 1959"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "A",
    "category": "Key Dates",
    "correct_answer_text": "1 November 1956"
  },
  {
    "id": 7,
    "question": "How many Lok Sabha seats in the state of Kerala?",
    "options": {
      "A": "18",
      "B": "30",
      "C": "20",
      "D": "23"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "C",
    "category": "History & Geography",
    "correct_answer_text": "20"
  },
  {
    "id": 8,
    "question": "What is the total number of elected representatives in Kerala legislative assembly?",
    "options": {
      "A": "140",
      "B": "120",
      "C": "150",
      "D": "None of the above"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "A",
    "category": "History & Geography",
    "correct_answer_text": "140"
  },
  {
    "id": 9,
    "question": "Name the first Chief Minister of Kerala State ?",
    "options": {
      "A": "E. M. S. Namboodiripad",
      "B": "Ikkanda Warrier",
      "C": "Panampilly Govinda Menon",
      "D": "None of the above"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "A",
    "category": "Social Reformers & Leaders",
    "correct_answer_text": "E. M. S. Namboodiripad"
  },
  {
    "id": 10,
    "question": "The First Europeans to come to Kerala was?",
    "options": {
      "A": "French",
      "B": "Portuguese",
      "C": "Dutch",
      "D": "British"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "B",
    "category": "History & Geography",
    "correct_answer_text": "Portuguese"
  },
  {
    "id": 11,
    "question": "First Malayalam Dictionary was compiled by ?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Hermann Gundert",
      "B": "Sreekanteswaram Padmanabha Pillai",
      "C": "Mahakavi Vallathol Narayana Menon",
      "D": "None of the above"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "A",
    "category": "Social Reformers & Leaders",
    "correct_answer_text": "Hermann Gundert"
  },
  {
    "id": 12,
    "question": "Who was the first woman governor of Kerala ?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Jyothi Venkitachalam",
      "B": "Fathima Beevi",
      "C": "Sarojini Naidu",
      "D": "Anna Chandy"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "A",
    "category": "Social Reformers & Leaders",
    "correct_answer_text": "Jyothi Venkitachalam"
  },
  {
    "id": 13,
    "question": "Which of the following explorers visited Kerala in 1498?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Vasco da Gama",
      "B": "John Cabot",
      "C": "Francis Drake",
      "D": "None of the above"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "A",
    "category": "Social Reformers & Leaders",
    "correct_answer_text": "Vasco da Gama"
  },
  {
    "id": 14,
    "question": "In which district of Kerala, the Silent Valley National Park is located?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Idukki",
      "B": "Palakkad",
      "C": "Kottayam",
      "D": "Wayanad"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "B",
    "category": "History & Geography",
    "correct_answer_text": "Palakkad"
  },
  {
    "id": 15,
    "question": "Which one city of Kerala is the major exporter of cashews in India?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Kollam",
      "B": "Munnar",
      "C": "Thrissur",
      "D": "Kochi"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "A",
    "category": "History & Geography",
    "correct_answer_text": "Kollam"
  },
  {
    "id": 16,
    "question": "Who is the longest serving Chief Minister of Kerala ?",
    "options": {
      "A": "AK Anthony",
      "B": "K Karunakaran",
      "C": "VS Achuthanandan",
      "D": "EK Nayanar"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "D",
    "category": "Social Reformers & Leaders",
    "correct_answer_text": "EK Nayanar"
  },
  {
    "id": 17,
    "question": "Kerala Land Reforms (Amendment) Act which put an end to the feudal system and ensured the rights of the tenants on land, came into force in",
    "options": {
      "A": "1957",
      "B": "1975",
      "C": "1970",
      "D": "1978"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "C",
    "category": "Key Dates",
    "correct_answer_text": "1970"
  },
  {
    "id": 18,
    "question": "The temple entry proclamation was associated with which of the following rulers ?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Swathi Thirunal",
      "B": "Sree Moolam Thirunal",
      "C": "Sri Chithira Thirunal",
      "D": "Ayilyam Thirunal"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "C",
    "category": "Social Reformers & Leaders",
    "correct_answer_text": "Sri Chithira Thirunal"
  },
  {
    "id": 19,
    "question": "Who was the founder of Atma Vidya sangam?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Kumara Guru Devan",
      "B": "Ayyankali",
      "C": "Chattampi Swamikal",
      "D": "Vagbhatananda"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "D",
    "category": "Social Reformers & Leaders",
    "correct_answer_text": "Vagbhatananda"
  },
  {
    "id": 20,
    "question": "Vaikom Satyagraha was started in the year",
    "options": {
      "A": "1924",
      "B": "1929",
      "C": "1932",
      "D": "1935"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "A",
    "category": "Key Dates",
    "correct_answer_text": "1924"
  },
  {
    "id": 21,
    "question": "Misrabhojanam was the idea popularised by",
    "options": {
      "A": "Mannathu Padmanabhan",
      "B": "Swami Vivekanandan",
      "C": "Sahodaran Ayyappan",
      "D": "Brahmananda Swami Sivayogi"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "C",
    "category": "Social Reformers & Leaders",
    "correct_answer_text": "Sahodaran Ayyappan"
  },
  {
    "id": 22,
    "question": "Who founded 'Advaita Ashram' at Aluva in 1913?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Chattampi Swamikal",
      "B": "Ayya Vaikundar",
      "C": "Thycaud Ayya",
      "D": "Sri Narayana Guru"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "D",
    "category": "Social Reformers & Leaders",
    "correct_answer_text": "Sri Narayana Guru"
  },
  {
    "id": 23,
    "question": "Who among the following is known as Kerala Gandhi ?",
    "options": {
      "A": "A.K. Gopalan",
      "B": "C. Kesavan",
      "C": "K. Kelappan",
      "D": "Ayyankali"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "C",
    "category": "Social Reformers & Leaders",
    "correct_answer_text": "K. Kelappan"
  },
  {
    "id": 24,
    "question": "Plachimada Struggle was conducted against-------",
    "options": {
      "A": "Coca Cola Company",
      "B": "Kannan Devan",
      "C": "Pepsico",
      "D": "Endosulfan"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "A",
    "category": "Movements & Politics",
    "correct_answer_text": "Coca Cola Company"
  },
  {
    "id": 25,
    "question": "Name the struggle conducted by SJVSV against the alienation of agricultural land",
    "options": {
      "A": "Kuttiadi",
      "B": "Plachimada",
      "C": "Chengara",
      "D": "None of the above"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "C",
    "category": "Movements & Politics",
    "correct_answer_text": "Chengara"
  },
  {
    "id": 26,
    "question": "Save Silent Valley, a social movement to protect silent valley was started in---",
    "options": {
      "A": "1965",
      "B": "1973",
      "C": "1984",
      "D": "1996"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "B",
    "category": "Key Dates",
    "correct_answer_text": "1973"
  },
  {
    "id": 27,
    "question": "Who was the head of the committee appointed by central government in 2010 to study the Western Ghats ecology",
    "options": {
      "A": "Sarkaria",
      "B": "Madhav Gadgil",
      "C": "Sadashiva Rao",
      "D": "BK Thapar"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "B",
    "category": "Social Reformers & Leaders",
    "correct_answer_text": "Madhav Gadgil"
  },
  {
    "id": 28,
    "question": "Kudumbasree was launched in the year---",
    "options": {
      "A": "1982",
      "B": "1988",
      "C": "1992",
      "D": "1998"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "D",
    "category": "Key Dates",
    "correct_answer_text": "1998"
  },
  {
    "id": 29,
    "question": "The struggle that led to the downfall of first Communist Ministry in Kerala",
    "options": {
      "A": "Kayyur Revolt",
      "B": "Vimochana Samaram",
      "C": "Kuttiadi Struggle",
      "D": "Abstention movement"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "B",
    "category": "Movements & Politics",
    "correct_answer_text": "Vimochana Samaram"
  },
  {
    "id": 30,
    "question": "Travancore State Congress was formed in",
    "options": {
      "A": "1921",
      "B": "1928",
      "C": "1938",
      "D": "1945"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "C",
    "category": "Key Dates",
    "correct_answer_text": "1938"
  },
  {
    "id": 31,
    "question": "Punnapra-Vayalar rebellion took place in the year------.",
    "options": {
      "A": "1940",
      "B": "1941",
      "C": "1942",
      "D": "1946"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "D",
    "category": "Key Dates",
    "correct_answer_text": "1946"
  },
  {
    "id": 32,
    "question": "Who became the first Chief Minister of Thiru-Cochi?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Ekkanda Warrier",
      "B": "Pattom Thanu Pillai",
      "C": "P. Govinda Menon",
      "D": "TK Narayana Pillai"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "D",
    "category": "Social Reformers & Leaders",
    "correct_answer_text": "TK Narayana Pillai"
  },
  {
    "id": 33,
    "question": "First General Election of Thiru-Cochi was held in",
    "options": {
      "A": "1947",
      "B": "1950",
      "C": "1951",
      "D": "1956"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "C",
    "category": "Key Dates",
    "correct_answer_text": "1951"
  },
  {
    "id": 34,
    "question": "Who is known as the father of Islamic renaissance in Kerala ?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Vakkom Maulavi",
      "B": "Abdul Rahman",
      "C": "Thangal Kunju",
      "D": "Muhammad Koya"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "A",
    "category": "Social Reformers & Leaders",
    "correct_answer_text": "Vakkom Maulavi"
  },
  {
    "id": 35,
    "question": "Name the publication launched by Vakkom Maulavi",
    "options": {
      "A": "Al- Ameen",
      "B": "Al Islam",
      "C": "Aligarh",
      "D": "Paschimodayam"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "B",
    "category": "Movements & Politics",
    "correct_answer_text": "Al Islam"
  },
  {
    "id": 36,
    "question": "Melsilakalapam was started by------",
    "options": {
      "A": "Nadars",
      "B": "Ezhavas",
      "C": "Tamil Brahmins",
      "D": "Muslims"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "A",
    "category": "Movements & Politics",
    "correct_answer_text": "Nadars"
  },
  {
    "id": 37,
    "question": "In which year was the Nivarthana Agitation?",
    "options": {
      "A": "1922",
      "B": "1923",
      "C": "1932",
      "D": "1933"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "C",
    "category": "Key Dates",
    "correct_answer_text": "1932"
  },
  {
    "id": 38,
    "question": "Who among the following worked for the emancipation of Namboothiri women?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Parvathy Nemenimangalam",
      "B": "Devika Antarjanam",
      "C": "Ambika Devi",
      "D": "KR Gouri"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "A",
    "category": "Social Reformers & Leaders",
    "correct_answer_text": "Parvathy Nemenimangalam"
  },
  {
    "id": 39,
    "question": "Who was the founder of the newspaper 'Swadeshabhimani'?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Ramakrishnapillai",
      "B": "GP Pillai",
      "C": "K. Kelappan",
      "D": "Vakkom Maulavi"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "D",
    "category": "Social Reformers & Leaders",
    "correct_answer_text": "Vakkom Maulavi"
  },
  {
    "id": 40,
    "question": "Who is regarded to be the initiator of Malayali Memorial?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Dr. Palpu",
      "B": "KB Menon",
      "C": "GP Pillai",
      "D": "AK Gopalan"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "C",
    "category": "Social Reformers & Leaders",
    "correct_answer_text": "GP Pillai"
  },
  {
    "id": 41,
    "question": "Which social reformer gave the slogan 'No caste, No religion, No God for man'?",
    "options": {
      "A": "KP Vallon",
      "B": "C Krishnan",
      "C": "Poikayil Yohannan",
      "D": "Sahodaran Ayyappan"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "D",
    "category": "Social Reformers & Leaders",
    "correct_answer_text": "Sahodaran Ayyappan"
  },
  {
    "id": 42,
    "question": "Electricity Agitation against the distribution of electricity in Cochi to a private company was started in the year----",
    "options": {
      "A": "1912",
      "B": "1922",
      "C": "1936",
      "D": "1946"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "C",
    "category": "Key Dates",
    "correct_answer_text": "1936"
  },
  {
    "id": 43,
    "question": "Who led the Kallumala (Stone Ornament) Agitation ?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Ayyankali",
      "B": "C Krishnan",
      "C": "Pandit K.P. Karuppan",
      "D": "Sahodaran Ayyappan"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "A",
    "category": "Social Reformers & Leaders",
    "correct_answer_text": "Ayyankali"
  },
  {
    "id": 44,
    "question": "Who has been hailed as the 'Father of Modern Kerala Renaissance'?",
    "options": {
      "A": "K Kelappan",
      "B": "EMS Namboothiripad",
      "C": "VT Bhattathiripad",
      "D": "Sree Narayana Guru"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "D",
    "category": "Social Reformers & Leaders",
    "correct_answer_text": "Sree Narayana Guru"
  },
  {
    "id": 45,
    "question": "Early inhabitants of Kerala belonged to the last phase of",
    "options": {
      "A": "Middle Stone Age",
      "B": "Early Stone Age",
      "C": "Iron Age",
      "D": "Copper Age"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "A",
    "category": "History & Geography",
    "correct_answer_text": "Middle Stone Age"
  },
  {
    "id": 46,
    "question": "The first recorded history of Kerala seems inside the inscriptions of",
    "options": {
      "A": "Bindusara",
      "B": "Ashoka",
      "C": "Pulakesin",
      "D": "Raj Raja I"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "B",
    "category": "History & Geography",
    "correct_answer_text": "Ashoka"
  },
  {
    "id": 47,
    "question": "Which was the main centre of Salt Satyagraha in Kerala?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Malabar",
      "B": "Cochin",
      "C": "Travancore",
      "D": "None of the above"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "A",
    "category": "History & Geography",
    "correct_answer_text": "Malabar"
  },
  {
    "id": 48,
    "question": "The earliest trade union in Kerala is",
    "options": {
      "A": "CITU",
      "B": "TLS",
      "C": "TLA",
      "D": "BMS"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "C",
    "category": "Movements & Politics",
    "correct_answer_text": "TLA"
  },
  {
    "id": 49,
    "question": "Leader of Adivasi Gothra Maha Sabha",
    "options": {
      "A": "C. K. Janu",
      "B": "K. C. Rosakkutti",
      "C": "M. Kamalam",
      "D": "None of the above"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "A",
    "category": "Social Reformers & Leaders",
    "correct_answer_text": "C. K. Janu"
  },
  {
    "id": 50,
    "question": "Which of the following organizations working for the welfare of queer community?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Sahayathrika",
      "B": "Sahayatra",
      "C": "Sahaya",
      "D": "None of the above"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "A",
    "category": "Movements & Politics",
    "correct_answer_text": "Sahayathrika"
  },
  {
    "id": 51,
    "question": "In which year the Presidential rule was enforced for the first time in Kerala State ?",
    "options": {
      "A": "1960",
      "B": "1959",
      "C": "1962",
      "D": "1964"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "B",
    "category": "Key Dates",
    "correct_answer_text": "1959"
  },
  {
    "id": 52,
    "question": "The People's Plan Campaign was introduced in the year",
    "options": {
      "A": "1994",
      "B": "1980",
      "C": "1996",
      "D": "1993"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "C",
    "category": "Key Dates",
    "correct_answer_text": "1996"
  },
  {
    "id": 53,
    "question": "Name the Dewan of Travancore associated with the 'American Model' administration?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Sir. C. P. Ramaswami Iyer",
      "B": "Sir. C. P. Ramaswami Iyyankar",
      "C": "Sir. C. P. Sankaran Nair",
      "D": "None of the above"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "A",
    "category": "Social Reformers & Leaders",
    "correct_answer_text": "Sir. C. P. Ramaswami Iyer"
  },
  {
    "id": 54,
    "question": "The first Land Reform Bill of the State of Kerala was introduced by",
    "options": {
      "A": "E. M. Sankaran Namboothiripad",
      "B": "T. V. Thomas",
      "C": "K. V. Thomas",
      "D": "K. R. Gauri"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "D",
    "category": "Social Reformers & Leaders",
    "correct_answer_text": "K. R. Gauri"
  },
  {
    "id": 55,
    "question": "When national emergency was in operation, the Chief Minister of Kerala was",
    "options": {
      "A": "Oommen Chandy",
      "B": "EK Nayanar",
      "C": "E.M. Sankaran Namboothiripad",
      "D": "C. Achutha Menon"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "D",
    "category": "Social Reformers & Leaders",
    "correct_answer_text": "C. Achutha Menon"
  },
  {
    "id": 56,
    "question": "The Nair Service Society was founded by",
    "options": {
      "A": "Sree Narayana Guru",
      "B": "Chattampi Swamikal",
      "C": "Mannath Padmanaabhan",
      "D": "None of the above"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "C",
    "category": "Social Reformers & Leaders",
    "correct_answer_text": "Mannath Padmanaabhan"
  },
  {
    "id": 57,
    "question": "Dutch power came to an end in Kerala with the battle of",
    "options": {
      "A": "Kolachel",
      "B": "Talikotta",
      "C": "Kayamkulam",
      "D": "Chaliyam"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "A",
    "category": "Movements & Politics",
    "correct_answer_text": "Kolachel"
  },
  {
    "id": 58,
    "question": "Kayyur riot was broke out in the year-------",
    "options": {
      "A": "1924",
      "B": "1931",
      "C": "1941",
      "D": "1944"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "C",
    "category": "Key Dates",
    "correct_answer_text": "1941"
  },
  {
    "id": 59,
    "question": "The land was owned by temples Known as",
    "options": {
      "A": "Devaswom",
      "B": "Pattam",
      "C": "Cherikkal",
      "D": "Kanam"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "A",
    "category": "History & Geography",
    "correct_answer_text": "Devaswom"
  },
  {
    "id": 60,
    "question": "The place in Kerala where Naval Academy is situated",
    "options": {
      "A": "Ezhimala",
      "B": "Marayoor",
      "C": "Thumba",
      "D": "Periya"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "A",
    "category": "History & Geography",
    "correct_answer_text": "Ezhimala"
  },
  {
    "id": 61,
    "question": "Who was the first opposition leader of Kerala legislative assembly ?",
    "options": {
      "A": "P.T.Chacko",
      "B": "Karunakaran",
      "C": "EMS Namboothiripad",
      "D": "AK Antony"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "A",
    "category": "Social Reformers & Leaders",
    "correct_answer_text": "P.T.Chacko"
  },
  {
    "id": 62,
    "question": "'Mamankom' was celebrated at ?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Thirunavaya",
      "B": "Thiruvalla",
      "C": "Thiruvananthapuram",
      "D": "Thiruchirapally"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "A",
    "category": "History & Geography",
    "correct_answer_text": "Thirunavaya"
  },
  {
    "id": 63,
    "question": "The name of the river that flows through the Silent Valley in Kerala ?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Kunthipuzha",
      "B": "Periyar",
      "C": "Chaliyar",
      "D": "Pamba"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "A",
    "category": "History & Geography",
    "correct_answer_text": "Kunthipuzha"
  },
  {
    "id": 64,
    "question": "Who was the first education minister of Kerala State ?",
    "options": {
      "A": "KR Gouri",
      "B": "Joseph Mundassery",
      "C": "TV Thomas",
      "D": "EMS Namboothiripad"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "B",
    "category": "Social Reformers & Leaders",
    "correct_answer_text": "Joseph Mundassery"
  },
  {
    "id": 65,
    "question": "The first Non Communist Chief Minister of Kerala ?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Pattom Thanu Pillai",
      "B": "Omman Chandy",
      "C": "AK Antony",
      "D": "EK Nayanar"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "A",
    "category": "Social Reformers & Leaders",
    "correct_answer_text": "Pattom Thanu Pillai"
  },
  {
    "id": 66,
    "question": "Sree Moolam Praja Sabha (Sree Moolam Popular Assembly) was formed in",
    "options": {
      "A": "1888",
      "B": "1940",
      "C": "1909",
      "D": "1904"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "D",
    "category": "Key Dates",
    "correct_answer_text": "1904"
  },
  {
    "id": 67,
    "question": "Who is the first chief minister from Kerala to be re-elected after completing a full term (five years) in office?",
    "options": {
      "A": "EK Nayanar",
      "B": "Omman Chandy",
      "C": "Pinarayi Vijayan",
      "D": "VS Achutanandan"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "C",
    "category": "Social Reformers & Leaders",
    "correct_answer_text": "Pinarayi Vijayan"
  },
  {
    "id": 68,
    "question": "Which party emerged due to the split of Communist Party of India in 1964?",
    "options": {
      "A": "RJD",
      "B": "Kerala Congress",
      "C": "Janata Party",
      "D": "CPI(M)"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "D",
    "category": "Movements & Politics",
    "correct_answer_text": "CPI(M)"
  },
  {
    "id": 69,
    "question": "The Government of Kerala enacted the Kerala Panchayati Raj and Municipality Act in which year ?",
    "options": {
      "A": "1993",
      "B": "1994",
      "C": "1995",
      "D": "1996"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "B",
    "category": "Key Dates",
    "correct_answer_text": "1994"
  },
  {
    "id": 70,
    "question": "--- is a programme for bridging the digital divide, promoting digital literacy and connecting communities in Kerala",
    "options": {
      "A": "Acharya",
      "B": "Abaya",
      "C": "Asraya",
      "D": "Akshaya"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "D",
    "category": "Movements & Politics",
    "correct_answer_text": "Akshaya"
  },
  {
    "id": 71,
    "question": "Who among the following is the editor of Mitavadi ?",
    "options": {
      "A": "A.K. Gopalan",
      "B": "C Krishnan",
      "C": "K. Kelappan",
      "D": "Ayyankali"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "B",
    "category": "Social Reformers & Leaders",
    "correct_answer_text": "C Krishnan"
  },
  {
    "id": 72,
    "question": "Which one of the following was a Christian missionary group in Kerala ?",
    "options": {
      "A": "LMS",
      "B": "CMS",
      "C": "BEM",
      "D": "All the above"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "D",
    "category": "Movements & Politics",
    "correct_answer_text": "All the above"
  },
  {
    "id": 73,
    "question": "Which one of the following customs was abolished by Sree Kerala Varma?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Pulappedi",
      "B": "Thalikettukalyanam",
      "C": "Untouchability",
      "D": "Sati"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "A",
    "category": "Movements & Politics",
    "correct_answer_text": "Pulappedi"
  },
  {
    "id": 74,
    "question": "'Wagon Tragedy' was in the year",
    "options": {
      "A": "1921",
      "B": "1922",
      "C": "1931",
      "D": "1932"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "A",
    "category": "Key Dates",
    "correct_answer_text": "1921"
  },
  {
    "id": 75,
    "question": "The first assembly election in Kerala state was held in",
    "options": {
      "A": "1957",
      "B": "1T959",
      "C": "1961",
      "D": "1963"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "A",
    "category": "Key Dates",
    "correct_answer_text": "1957"
  },
  {
    "id": 76,
    "question": "Which of the following organizations aimed at women's welfare?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Sahaja",
      "B": "Sahayathrika",
      "C": "Anweshi",
      "D": "All of the above"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "D",
    "category": "Movements & Politics",
    "correct_answer_text": "All of the above"
  },
  {
    "id": 77,
    "question": "Leader of Sadhu Jana Vimochana Samyukta Vedi ?",
    "options": {
      "A": "C. K. Janu",
      "B": "Laha Gopalan",
      "C": "M. Mukundan",
      "D": "None of the above"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "B",
    "category": "Social Reformers & Leaders",
    "correct_answer_text": "Laha Gopalan"
  },
  {
    "id": 78,
    "question": "On which of the following days Kerala statehood is observed ?",
    "options": {
      "A": "November 1st",
      "B": "December 1st",
      "C": "August 1st",
      "D": "October 1st"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "A",
    "category": "Movements & Politics",
    "correct_answer_text": "November 1st"
  },
  {
    "id": 79,
    "question": "The famous Kerala born Indian philosopher of 9th cent AD",
    "options": {
      "A": "Sankaraachaarya",
      "B": "Sree Narayana Guru",
      "C": "Kautilya",
      "D": "None of the above"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "A",
    "category": "Social Reformers & Leaders",
    "correct_answer_text": "Sankaraachaarya"
  },
  {
    "id": 80,
    "question": "The basic issue mentioned in Malayali Memorial was",
    "options": {
      "A": "Religious rights",
      "B": "Right to property",
      "C": "Intercaste marriage",
      "D": "Government jobs"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "D",
    "category": "Movements & Politics",
    "correct_answer_text": "Government jobs"
  },
  {
    "id": 81,
    "question": "The first organisation of the Pariah community in Travancore was?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Brahma Prathyaksha Sadhujana Paripalana Sangam",
      "B": "Yogakshema Sabha",
      "C": "SNDP",
      "D": "NSS"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "A",
    "category": "Movements & Politics",
    "correct_answer_text": "Brahma Prathyaksha Sadhujana Paripalana Sangam"
  },
  {
    "id": 82,
    "question": "Major organization which gave leadership to Muthanga Land Struggle is",
    "options": {
      "A": "Sadhu Jana Vimochana Munnani",
      "B": "Kerala Harijans Federation",
      "C": "Adivasi Gothra Maha Sabha",
      "D": "Kerala Sastra Sahitya Parishad"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "C",
    "category": "Movements & Politics",
    "correct_answer_text": "Adivasi Gothra Maha Sabha"
  },
  {
    "id": 83,
    "question": "Which of the following programmes was to reduce and control environmental pollution to a certain extent?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Akshaya",
      "B": "Ashraya",
      "C": "Janasree",
      "D": "Haritha Keralam"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "D",
    "category": "Movements & Politics",
    "correct_answer_text": "Haritha Keralam"
  },
  {
    "id": 84,
    "question": "Name of the toxic pesticide that poisoned almost everything on the surface and beneath the earth in Kasargod?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Ammonia",
      "B": "DDT",
      "C": "Endosulfan",
      "D": "None of the above"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "C",
    "category": "Movements & Politics",
    "correct_answer_text": "Endosulfan"
  },
  {
    "id": 85,
    "question": "Ruler of a 'Nadu' in medieval Kerala is known as",
    "options": {
      "A": "Nadu Thalaivan",
      "B": "Nadu Pramukh",
      "C": "Naduvazhi",
      "D": "Mooppan"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "C",
    "category": "History & Geography",
    "correct_answer_text": "Naduvazhi"
  },
  {
    "id": 86,
    "question": "Who opined that Kerala is a mad house of castes",
    "options": {
      "A": "Swami Vivekananda",
      "B": "Gandhiji",
      "C": "Sree Narayana Guru",
      "D": "Nehru"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "A",
    "category": "Social Reformers & Leaders",
    "correct_answer_text": "Swami Vivekananda"
  },
  {
    "id": 87,
    "question": "National Democratic Alliance (NDA) in Kerala is led by",
    "options": {
      "A": "CPM",
      "B": "Kerala Congress",
      "C": "BJP",
      "D": "Indian National Congress"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "C",
    "category": "Movements & Politics",
    "correct_answer_text": "BJP"
  },
  {
    "id": 88,
    "question": "What is SPEM?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Societal Pollution Eradication Mission",
      "B": "State Pollution Eradication Mission",
      "C": "Social Poverty Eradication Mission",
      "D": "State Poverty Eradication Mission"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "D",
    "category": "Movements & Politics",
    "correct_answer_text": "State Poverty Eradication Mission"
  },
  {
    "id": 89,
    "question": "Who was the Chief Minister of Kerala during the period 2011-2016 ?",
    "options": {
      "A": "EK Nayanar",
      "B": "Omman Chandy",
      "C": "Pinarayi Vijayan",
      "D": "None of the above"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "B",
    "category": "Social Reformers & Leaders",
    "correct_answer_text": "Omman Chandy"
  },
  {
    "id": 90,
    "question": "When was bicameralism introduced in Travancore?",
    "options": {
      "A": "1925",
      "B": "1932",
      "C": "1935",
      "D": "1942"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "B",
    "category": "Key Dates",
    "correct_answer_text": "1932"
  },
  {
    "id": 91,
    "question": "Which among the following is a feature of Kerala Model of Development?",
    "options": {
      "A": "High Per Capita Income",
      "B": "High infant mortality rate",
      "C": "High standard of living",
      "D": "High economic investment"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "C",
    "category": "Movements & Politics",
    "correct_answer_text": "High standard of living"
  },
  {
    "id": 92,
    "question": "The Guruvayur temple was thrown open to Harijans only after ?",
    "options": {
      "A": "1940",
      "B": "1942",
      "C": "1944",
      "D": "1946"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "D",
    "category": "Key Dates",
    "correct_answer_text": "1946"
  },
  {
    "id": 93,
    "question": "The merger of Travancore and Cochin was realized in the year?",
    "options": {
      "A": "1949",
      "B": "1956",
      "C": "1950",
      "D": "1947"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "A",
    "category": "Key Dates",
    "correct_answer_text": "1949"
  },
  {
    "id": 94,
    "question": "The first member of Pulaya community to be nominated to Travancore Legislative Assembly",
    "options": {
      "A": "T.T.Kesavan Sasthri",
      "B": "P.C.Chanchen",
      "C": "Pandit Karuppan",
      "D": "Ayyankali"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "D",
    "category": "Social Reformers & Leaders",
    "correct_answer_text": "Ayyankali"
  },
  {
    "id": 95,
    "question": "Name the prime minister who visited Kerala during the Liberation Struggle ?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Indira Gandhi",
      "B": "Lal Bahadur Shastri",
      "C": "Jawaharlal Nehru",
      "D": "Morarjee Desai"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "C",
    "category": "Social Reformers & Leaders",
    "correct_answer_text": "Jawaharlal Nehru"
  },
  {
    "id": 96,
    "question": "The founder of Sambavar Sangam",
    "options": {
      "A": "Pazhoor Raman Chennan",
      "B": "Ayyankali",
      "C": "Chattampi Swamikal",
      "D": "Pandit Karuppan"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "A",
    "category": "Social Reformers & Leaders",
    "correct_answer_text": "Pazhoor Raman Chennan"
  },
  {
    "id": 97,
    "question": "The founder of All Travancore Muslim Mahajanasabha",
    "options": {
      "A": "Mohammed Hammadani",
      "B": "Abdul Rahman",
      "C": "Thangal Kunju",
      "D": "Vakkom Abdul Khadar Moulavi"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "D",
    "category": "Social Reformers & Leaders",
    "correct_answer_text": "Vakkom Abdul Khadar Moulavi"
  },
  {
    "id": 98,
    "question": "Cochin Pulaya Maha Sabha was founded by",
    "options": {
      "A": "Ayyankali",
      "B": "T.T.Kesavan Sasthri",
      "C": "Pandit Karuppan",
      "D": "None of these"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "C",
    "category": "Social Reformers & Leaders",
    "correct_answer_text": "Pandit Karuppan"
  },
  {
    "id": 99,
    "question": "The only foreign country visited by Sree Narayana Guru",
    "options": {
      "A": "Nepal",
      "B": "Bhutan",
      "C": "Burma",
      "D": "Sri Lanka"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "D",
    "category": "Social Reformers & Leaders",
    "correct_answer_text": "Sri Lanka"
  },
  {
    "id": 100,
    "question": "The motto of Kerala Sasthra Sahitya Parishad",
    "options": {
      "A": "Knowledge is power",
      "B": "Sasthram Samoohika Viplavathinu",
      "C": "Vayichu Valaruka",
      "D": "Sakshara Keralam Sundara Keralam"
    },
    "correct_answer_key": "B",
    "category": "Movements & Politics",
    "correct_answer_text": "Sasthram Samoohika Viplavathinu"
  }
]
